RESUME



PERSONAL DETAILS

Name Dr. Viraj Hanumantrao Mankar

Fathers Name Mr. Hanumantrao Nivrutti Mankar

Date of Birth 15th April 1983

Nationality Indian

Languages Known English, Hindi, Marathi (Read, Write, Speak)

Gender Male

Marital Status Married

Mailing Address At- Mankarwadi, Post- Kurawali

Taluka- Indapur, District- Pune

Pin- 413104

Email <u>drmankarviraj@gmail.com</u>,

mankarviraj@yahoo.com.au

Contact Number +91 8668854800, 9779282899,

SUMMARY

I completed my PhD at Queensland University of Technology in Brisbane Australia. My PhD research was focused on synthesis and biological evaluation of novel dual action cardio-protective agents. This project is heavily weighted in free radical antioxidant synthesis with a biological application including cancer, diabetes and cardiovascular diseases. My strengths are in the synthesis of biologically active chemical entities; however, I am willing to work in new areas of research. I have great focus and perseverance in any task I am given. I get great satisfaction working on novel ideas which are challenging and researching better techniques. I have great communication skills; have attended many conferences, given seminars in my work. I have total experience of 13 years out of which 4 years in the PhD new drug discovery and 4 years in pharmaceutical API process development R&D(after MSc) and 5 years of full time teaching experience in engineering chemistry, environmental studies, applied Chemistry and also in core organic chemistry as assistant Professor in Lovely Professional University Punjab.

......

EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND

<u>Degree/</u>	<u>Year of</u>	Board/	Subject/	<u>Percentage</u>	<u>Class</u>
Examination	<u>Passing</u>	<u>University</u>	<u>Specialization</u>		
SSC	1998	Pune	_	55.86	Higher Second
HSC	2000	Pune	Science	58.00	Higher Second
BSc	2004	Pune	Chemistry	67.68	First
MSc	2006	Pune	Drug Chemistry	58.45	Higher Second
PhD	2016	QUT, Brisbane, Australia	Synthetic Medicinal Chemistry	_	_
MSCIT	2003	M.S.B.T.E., Mumbai	Computer	63	First
EAP	2011	QUT, Brisbane, Australia	Academic English	67	First

WORK EXPERIENCE

Total year of Research Experience 13 Years 0 months

Working at Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia as 'PhD Research'.
 Dept. of Nanotechnology and Molecular Sciences
 Period: February 2011 to May 2015. (Experience 4 Year).

- Design and synthesis of dual action adenosine compounds combining with nitroxide antioxidants.
- Good knowledge of synthesis and purification of large molecular mass of profloroscent and biologically active molecules.
- Proficient in carrying-out independent and collaborative research.
- Experience in synthetic and medicinal organic chemistry.
- Sound knowledge of commonly used chemistry related software's and instruments.
- Extensive knowledge of compound purification and characterization by HPLC, MPLC, ESR, NMR, IR, Mass analysis.
- Good knowledge of radical chemistry and related reactions.
- Knowledge of carbohydrate chemistry, purine chemistry and dual action compounds on GPCRs.
- Dual action antioxidant combining cardio-protective compounds.
- Nitroxide-antioxidant chemistry.
- Experience in training undergraduate research students in the laboratory.

2. Working at Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia as 'Sessional Academic Staff' Member. (Part time)

Dept. Nanotechnology and Molecular Sciences

Period: July 2013 to October 2015. (Experience 2 Year and 4 months)

- Attentive chemistry lecturer with excellent communication skills.
- Conducts college level courses in the field of chemistry.
- Expertise in Planning, preparing and delivering lectures and leading classroom discussions and laboratory demonstrations.

3. Working at Merck/ Mylan India Pvt Limited, Taloja, Navi-Mumbai as 'Research Executive'.

Dept. Research & Development (Synthetic Organic Chemistry).

Period: June 2006 to February 2010. (Experience 3 Year and 8 months)

- Design and development of the novel route for the synthesis of active pharmaceutical ingredient (API) laboratory scale following literature and in-house procedures.
- Demonstrate the process to kilo lab and pilot plant to validate the process of synthesis.
- Develop and optimize the process for synthesis of the highest quality API using multi-stage synthesis.

- Extensive knowledge of purification, identification and characterization of drug molecules and impurities by HPLC, NMR, IR, Mass analysis.
- Knowledge of good manufacturing practices (GMP) campaign works in cross functional teams for monitoring raw material and final product specification generation, raw material procurement, analytical method validation, process validation.
- Ability to work in coordination with process engineers and plant operators for successful technology transfer from lab to pilot plant.
- Familiar with chemical hygiene and safe handling procedures in the laboratory.
- Successfully commercialized API Sitagliptin, Frovatriptan, Zofenopril, Pregabalin on the continued production scale.
- 4. Working in Lovely Professional University, Phagwara, Punjab as Assistant Professor School of Chemical Engineering and Physical Sciences and School of Civil and Mechanical engineering Period: starting from August 2016 to till date. (Experience: 4.5 year) current.
 - Attentive chemistry lecturer with excellent communication skills.
 - Conducts college level courses in the field of chemistry.
 - ♦ Expertise in areas of instruction includes organic chemistry, chemical analysis, and chemical reactions.
 - Planning, preparing and delivering lectures and leading classroom discussions.
 - Administering and grading examinations and giving appropriate feedback to students.
 - Ability to work both independently and in team environments.
 - Coordinate the workflow for a team, including resource planning, scheduling, and prioritizing workload to identify and resolve issues.
 - Familiar with a variety of the chemistry concepts, practices, and procedures.
 - Experience and judgment to plan and accomplish goals.
 - Performs a variety of tasks, lead and direct the work of others.
 - Tailoring chemistry teaching methods to suit the need of individual student.
 - Devising and writing new curriculum materials.
 - Preparing coursework for students and the class.
 - Recording and monitoring student's attendance.
 - Good experience in the synthesis of drugs and other biologically active molecules.
 - Proficient in carrying-out independent and collaborative research.
 - Doctorate degree experience in synthetic and medicinal organic chemistry.
 - Sound knowledge of commonly used chemistry related software's and instruments.
 - Sound knowledge of compound purification and characterization by HPLC, MPLC, EPR, NMR, IR, Mass analysis.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Course Code	Course Title	Term Id	<u>Year</u>
CHE124	Engineering Chemistry Theory	16171-17182	2016-2020
CHE122	Engineering Chemistry Laboratory	16171-17182	2016-2020
CHE110	Environmental Studies	16171-17181	2016-2020
CHE115	Basic Organic Chemistry Theory	16172- 18191	2017-2019
CHE882	Chemistry in Daily Life Theory	16172	2017-2018
CHE585	MSc Organic Chemistry Laboratory-II	17182-18191	2018-19
CHE638	MSc Organic Chemistry Laboratory-III	17181	2017-18
CHE01D	Applied Chemistry-I	20211	2019-20

PROJECT WORK (DURING MASTERS OF SCIENCE)

"Standardization of Herb- Terminalia bellerica" (June- August 2005) Hi-Tech Biosciences, Paud Road, Kothrude, Pune.

RESEARCH GUIDANCE

Guided Seven MSc Research Project Students

Guidance two PhD Research Students- Current

VOLUNTEER WORK

- ◆ Pulse Polio Campaign, Baramati 2003.
- ♦ National Service Scheme Special Campaign 2002-2004.
- ♦ Blood Donation Campaign **2011**.
- ◆ Participate in Cultural Society of India, Brisbane.2012.
- ◆ Participate in Radical Wine and Chocolate Festival 9 Aug 2013.

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

Research patents, Book and papers published/ communicated in peer reviewed international journals

- Patent Gore, V. G.; Datta, D.; Gadakar, M.; Pokharkar, K.; Mankar, V.; Wavhal, S. A novel process of preparing an enantiomerically enriched γ-amino acid, such as enantiomerically enriched (S)-pregabalin. In Espacenet Patents: WO2009122215 A1: 2009.
- 2. <u>Patent-</u> Gore, V. G.; Gadkar, M.; Tripathi, A.; **Mankar, V**. A process for the preparation of frovatriptan and frovatriptan succinate and their synthetic intermediates. In Espacenet Patents WO2010122343 A1: 2010..
- 3. Book on "Cardiovascular Protection with Adenosine Combined Antioxidants" 2018 Lambert Publication.
- 4. **A review on edaravone as potential antioxidants**, *Plant Archives*, Vol. 20, Supplement 2, 2020 pp. 3192-3198.
- 5. Edaravone based antioxidants for cardioprotection and neuroprotection, *Plant Archives*, Vol. 20, Supplement 2, 2020 pp. 3440-3445.
- 6. **Sterically Hindered Phenols as Antioxidant**, *European Journal of Molecular and Clinical Medicine*, Issue 7, Volume 7, 2020 pp3481-3491.
- 7. Technical advancement of cadmium and lead detection methods and Future scope for biosensor in Dairy industry: An Overview, Sambodhi UGC care journal Issue 4, Volume 43, 2020 pp140-147.

NATIONAL/ INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES/ SYMPOSIA ATTENDED/PRESENTED

- 1. National Conference on Recent Advances in Chemical Sciences (Food and Drug Research), **Bikaner**, **Rajasthan (3-5 Oct 2008).**
- 2. Bio-Nano Innovation International Conference, Brisbane, Australia (18-20 July 2012).
- 3. ARC Free Radical Chemistry Conference, Sydney, Australia (Dec 2012).
- 4. ARC Free Radical Chemistry Conference, University of Wollongong, Wollongong,

Australia (Dec 2013)

- 5. Brisbane Biological and Organic Chemistry Symposium (BBOCS), Griffith University, Brisbane, Australia (Dec 2013).
- 6. Brisbane Biological and Organic Chemistry Symposium (BBOCS), Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia (1 Dec 2014).
 Poster presentation was done in above conference with title "Synthesis and Biological Evaluation of Novel Nitroxide Antioxidant Containing Adenosine A2A Agonists for Cardio-protection".
- 7. RACI National Congress, International Conference, Adelaide, Australia (7-12 Dec 2014).
 - Poster presentation was done in above conference with title I) "Synthesis and Biological Evaluation of Dual Acting Nitroxide Antioxidant A2A Agonists for Cardio-protection".
 - And II) "Radicals New Weapons in the Battle Against Inflammation".
- International Conference on Recent Advances in Fundamental and Applied Sciences (RAFAS), Lovely Professional University, Phagwara, Punjab (25-26 Nov 2016)
 Organizing committee member and worked as abstract and full paper reviewer
- 9. National Conference on Recent trends in Physical, Chemical, and Biosciences, (*RTPCB-2016*), V.P. College, Baramati (16-17 Dec 2016). Worked as National advisory committee member.
- 10. Inter-**Disciplinary Seminar** on Sustainable Urbanization, Environment and Spatial Planning Concerns Dec 17-19 2018 UGC-Human Resource Development Centre, Guru Nanak Dev University, Amritsar
- 11. **106**th **Indian Science Congress**, Lovely Professional University, Phagwara, Punjab (3-7 Jan 2019) Organizing committee member and Poster presentation.
- 12. International Conference on Continuity Consistency and innovation in Applied Sciences and Humanities, **Technical advancement of cadmium and lead detection methods and Future scope for biosensor in Dairy industry: An Overview** (ICCIASH-2020)(13-14 Aug 2020)

AWARDS

- 1. QUT PhD Student Living Allowance Scholarships, 2011-2015.
- QUT PhD Tuition Fee Waiver Scholarships, 2011-2015.
- 3. QUT Academic Development Foundation of Learning and Teaching Certificate (22 May 2015).
- 4. QUT Academic Development Sessional Academic Program Certificate (17 Apr 2014).
- 5. Certificate of Friendship by the Lord Mayer of Brisbane Councilor Graham Quirk (29 Aug 2013).
- 6. National Service Scheme (NSS) Certificate, University of Pune, 2002-2004.
- Maharashtra State Certificate in Information Technology (MS-CIT), Oct -2003.
- National Workshop on Environmental Sciences, Lovely Professional University, Jan-2018.

MEMBERSHIP

- 1. Life member of Indian Science Congress
- 2. Associate Editor of "International Journal of PharmTech Research".
- 3. Editorial Board Member "American Journal of Chemical Research"
- 4. Science Journal of Chemistry (SJC),
- 5. Journal of Drug Design and Medicinal Chemistry(JDDMC);
- 6. International Journal Chemistry Studies
- 7. International Journal of Green Chemistry

REFERENCES

Professor Steven. E. Bottle

Research Supervisor
Chief Investigator and leader,
Queensland Node
Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence:
Free Radical Chemistry and Biotechnology
Queensland University of Technology.
GPO Box 2434
Brisbane, Queensland, Australia 4000.

Tel: +61 7 3138 1356 Fax: +61 7 3138 1804 Email: s.bottle@qut.edu.au Web: www.freeradical.org.au

Dr. Lalasaheb Kashid

Vice-Principal, V. P. College, Baramati Pin No- 413102, INDIA Email- Imkashid@gmail.com Phone no. 9860001643

Dr. Vijay Khanna

Professor of Drug Chemistry Ahmednagar College, Ahmednagar, Pin No- 414001, INDIA Phone (Office): +91-241-2324024 E-mail: vijaykhanna@hotmail.com

Dr. S. Ravichandran,

HOD, Associate Professor in Chemistry, School of Chemical Engineering and Physical Sciences, Lovely Professional University, Jalandhar - Delhi GT Road, Phagwara - 144 411 Phone (Office): +91-9840735064 Email- rayichandran.23324@lpu.co.in

ravichandru@yahoo.com